Hello! In this episode of Bug Bounty Reports
Explained, you will learn how "try weird stuff and
see what happens" methodology led the bughunter,
Teddy Katz to a critical vulnerability in GitHub.
it allowed stealing GitHub api token and other
secrets from GitHub actions using a malicious
pull request. The reward for the bug was $25,000.
Link to the original report is in the description.
Make sure to check out other write-ups on Teddy's
blog because those are one of the coolest bugs
I have ever seen. But for now, enjoy the video!
First, I am going to explain commits, branches,
pull requests and forks in git. If you are already
familiar with these topics, skip this part of the
video using chapters feature on YouTube. Git is
a system version control. It allows developers
to work on the product together simultaneously
by synchronizing changes between them.
After creating some code, a developer creates
a commit. It's a snapshot of the project after
his changes. Even if developers start adding more
code on top of this, this commit with the project
at this exact stage will always stay there and you
will be able to come back to it. And commits are
identified using 40 character hex strings.
And sometimes, when you develop a feature,
you might want to commit your work at the end of
the day even though the code doesn't work yet.
But committing such code may break the program
for other users. To avoid that you may create a
separate branch where you develop the feature.
In the meantime, the main branch will live its
own life. For example, a critical security
vulnerability might be fixed there. Now, what
happens when you finished developing your feature
and you want to merge it into the main branch?
You create a pull request. It's a way to notify
other developers in the project that the feature
is ready to be in the main branch. After the pull
request is accepted, the feature gets merged and
it's available to other users. But what if you
are using your favourite script from GitHub
and you notice a bug. You may be the good guy and
you don't want to just notify the project that
there is an issue but you are good enough to fix
it yourself. And maybe you'd like to push this fix
to other users as well. But, of course, you don't
have access to the main repository because no one
knows you. You may then fork the repository. It
means copy it to your own GitHub account. You may
implement the fix there and once it's finished you
can create a pull request to the main repository.
Importantly, each pull request has a base branch.
So when creating a pull request you tell git
to which branch of the main project
you'd like to merge your code into.
And here is where our hunter comes in. This is the
part of the request that creates a pull request.
baseRefName is the parameter which tells
git to which branch you want to merge.
The hunter asked himself a
question: what would happen
if instead of putting the branch name there he
would put a 40 character commit hash instead.
It would be a bug but it's unclear what would be
the impact of this. But he didn't have to worry
about the potential impact because it didn't
even work. The response contained a message
"base must be a branch". But you wouldn't be
watching this video if it ended like this...
Turned out that the check was there when
creating a pull request but there was no
validation when editing it. So you could create a
valid pull request to the branch and then edit it
so that the baseRefName is a commit hash.
But there is still no impact to this.
So it's time to introduce GitHub actions.
It's a way to automate processes on GitHub.
You can specify some action, for example running
tests on your code, that occurs after a specific
event, for example creating a pull request. The
action may also do things like adding labels to
issues or deploying your code to a
server. And when GitHub runs your code,
for example to run tests, it does that in a
sandbox environment in order to be more secure.
But some of your actions like deploying your code
to a server may require some credentials to be
accessible from the workflow. That's why in the
repository you can define some secrets. Those are
of course confidential and not accessible when
you clone or fork the repository. By default,
one secret is created for each repository -
GitHub API token with write access to the repo.
And when you create a pull request, repo
maintainers may want to run tests on your code
to see if it didn't break anything. This triggers
the pull_request action and the workflow starts.
It simulates merging your code with the base
branch and running the application. In your fork,
you may make some changes to the workflow
configuration. In case of the pull_request event,
your code will be used to run the workflow. This,
obviously, creates a huge risk because you could
achieve a remote code execution in many ways.
That's why this action doesn't have access to
secrets from the repository. There is only GitHub
API token but only with read access to the repo.
This can be used to securely
run tests on untrusted code.
But without the GitHub API token with write
access, the workflow will not be able to,
for example, add label to the pull request. That's
why there is another type of action triggered
after a pull request: pull_request_target. The
difference is that when you create a pull request,
this action doesn't run your code. It runs the
code from the branch to which you want to merge.
The code just before your changes. It's usually
used to add labels or comments to pull requests
because the code just before your
changes was created by someone with write
access to the repo which means that
this code is trusted and secure.That's
why this type of workflow will have
access to secrets from GitHub repo.
Let's now connect all the
dots together for an exploit.
So first, you fork victim repository which
means you copy it to your GitHub account.
Then, you make some changes that are
completely irrelevant at the moment.
Then, you create a pull request to
victim repository, to the main branch.
This triggers the pull_request action that runs
your code but without access to secrets. Next,
coming back to your forked repository, you
create a malicious commit. You create a
workflow that steals GitHub API token and sends
it to your server. This workflow is triggered
by the pull_request_target action and this is
an example configuration file with the workflow.
Next, you come back to the pull request in victim
repository. You edit the base branch of the pull
request but now instead of putting the branch
you put there a hash of your malicious commit
from the previous step. It works because for
GitHub commit for a repo is a commit and doesn't
matter if it was in fork or not. So now you have
the strange situation where you have the pull
request in the victim repository where you make
some changes to your own code. But importantly,
GitHub doesn't know that. Usually, the
base of the pull request is trusted code
so in this case GitHub treats your
malicious commit as trusted. That's why
it can trigger the pull_request_target
action using configuration from your
malicious commit. Then, your code is run
with full access to repository secrets.
Then, you can exfiltrate GitHub API token and
other secrets to your server thus taking over the
repository and potentially other services as well.
The reward for the bug was $25,000 which was the
middle of the range for critical vulnerabilities
on GitHub. As for the fix, the base branch of the
pull request must actually be a branch now. And
that's it. For me, it happened a few times that I
identified a strange behaviour in the application
but there was no real impact. I'm also interested
in your stories of strange bugs with or without
the impact. I will be waiting for you in the
comments down below. I will start with one of my
stories first. Anyway, if you enjoyed the video,
leave a like and leave a subscription. For
now thank you for watching and goodbye!